Guide to the Railsback Family Correspondence 1909-1923
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Railsback Family Correspondence
1909-1923
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 627
Railsback Family
1.0 linear foot
This collection contains early correspondence between members of the Railsback family of Montana, the personal correspondence of Edna Railsback, and miscellaneous papers, clippings, and notes from 1909-1923.
Biographical Note
The Railsbacks were an early ranching family from Billings, Montana. Edmund O. and Lucy Railsback were the parents of Jesse and Edna Railsback. Edmund was a former stockman who died in 1946 at the estimated age of 86. He resided in Billings from the 1890s until 1941. He spent the last 5 years of his life at the Masonic home in Helena. He had been active in Masonic lodges throughout most of his life. His wife, Lucy Railsback, an early school teacher in the Billings schools, died in 1926. Their daughter, Jessie Railsback, was a student at the University of Montana and a member of the Kappa Kappa Gamma sorority. She was a sophomore in 1914, when the majority of her letters were written. Edna lived in Billings during the years of this collection and also spent time in Illinois.
This collection contains early correspondence between members of the Railsback family, the personal correspondence of Edna Railsback, and miscellaneous papers, clippings, and notes from 1909-1923. Jessie Railsback’s letters home offer insight into early student life at the University of Montana, including dorm life and sorority membership. Correspondence to Edna Railsback from various friends and family covered general topics such as daily happenings or recent news
Letters from Jessie Railsback to family are most often addressed to Mrs. Edmund O. Railsback but some are addressed to Miss Edna Railsback, who apparently was living at home at the time. Most letters begin with “To Folks,” therefore they are all placed in the same category.
The collection is divided into three series:
Series I: Correspondence between Railsback family members, 1910-1914
Series II: Correspondence to Edna Railsback, 1909-1913
Series III: Miscellaneous, 1911-1923
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
Materials were held by Bard G. Middleton until he donated the papers in 2005
Gift of Bard G. Middleton, 2005
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Railsback, Edmund, 1859-1946--Correspondence; Railsback, Edna L., b. 1888--Correspondence; Railsback, Jessie A., b.1884--Correspondence; Railsback, Lucy S., 1860-1926--Correspondence
Railsback family
Kappa Kappa Gamma; State University of Montana (Missoula)--Students--Correspondence
Greek letter societies--Montana--Missoula; Women college students--Montana--Missoula--Correspondence
Family papers--Montana--Billings
Student Life; Missoula; Montana; Women; Home and Family
- Correspondence between Railsback family members, 1910-1914; Series I
  - To Mrs. Edmund O. Railsback, from Jessie Railsback, August 11, 1910-January 28, 1914 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - To Mrs. Edmund O. Railsback, from Jessie Railsback, January 29, 1914-February 13, 1914 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - To Mrs. Edmund O. Railsback, from Jessie Railsback, February 17, 1914-March 8, 1914 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - To Mrs. Edmund O. Railsback, from Jessie Railsback, March 15, 1914-April 2, 1914 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - To Mrs. Edmund O. Railsback, from Jessie Railsback, April 4, 1914-May 2, 1914 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - To Mrs. Edmund O. Railsback, from Jessie Railsback, May 6, 1914-May 27, 1914 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - To Mrs. Edmund O. Railsback, from Jessie Railsback (Box-folder 1/7)
  - To Mrs. Edmund O. Railsback, from Edna Railsback, September 30, 1913-October 14, 1913 and undated (Box-folder 1/8)
  - To Edna Railsback, from Mrs. Edmund O. Railsback, March 19, 1914 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - To Jessie Railsback, from Edna Railsback, October 19, 1911-October 7, 1913 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - To Edna Railsback, from Mrs. J.B. Smith, 1910-1911 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - To Edna Railsback, from Cousin Olive, 1911-1912 (Box-folder 1/12)
- Correspondence to Edna Railsback, 1909-1913; Series II
  - To Edna Railsback, from Annie Frank, 1910-1911 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - To Edna Railsback, from Fred, 1910-1911 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - To Edna Railsback, from Fred, 1911-1912 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - To Edna Railsback, from Edna Hoskins, 1909-1911 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - To Edna Railsback, from Edna Hoskins, 1911-1912 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - To Edna Railsback, from Brainard Mears, 1909-1910 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - To Edna Railsback, from Phyllis, 1910-1912 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - To Edna Railsback, from "Shorty", 1909 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - To Edna Railsback, from Sic, 1910-1911 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - To Edna Railsback, from Hubert M. Turner, 1910-1912 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - To Edna Railsback, from Lillian W., 1910-1912 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - To Edna Railsback, Miscellaneous, May 18, 1906-November 13, 1910 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - To Edna Railsback, Miscellaneous, December 19, 1910-May 27, 1911 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - To Edna Railsback, Miscellaneous, August 24, 1911-May 1, 1912 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - To Edna Railsback, Miscellaneous, June 19, 1912-June 10, 1913 (Box-folder 2/12)
- Miscellaneous, 1911-1923; Series III
  - Miscellaneous letters, 1911-1913 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Miscellaneous papers, clipping, poem, undated (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Miscellaneous school notes, undated (Box-folder 2/15)